<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jesuites plea In ansvver to a letter written by a minister, entituled, Lying allowable with papists to deceive Protestants.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828297</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46860)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1950:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jesuites plea In ansvver to a letter written by a minister, entituled, Lying allowable with papists to deceive Protestants.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Minister of the Church of England. --  Lying allowable with papists to deceive Protestants --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32724:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Ieſuites Plea.</hi> IN ANSVVER TO A LETTER WRITTEN BY A MINISTER, <hi>ENTIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LED, Lying allowable with</hi> PAPISTS <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> PROTESTANTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:32724:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32724:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE <hi>Ieſuit's Plea.</hi>
               </hi> In ANSWER to a LETTER Written By A MINISTER, ENTITULED, <hi>Lying allowable with</hi> PAPISTS <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> PROTESTANTS.</head>
            <p>I Should be extreamly unjuſt, if I in the leaſt doubted ſincerity in the ſolemn Aſſeverations of the late Executed <hi>Jeſuites</hi> at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> for I muſt ſuppoſe them either <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> or no <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts;</hi> if <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> What would they not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> done or confeſſed to ſave their Lives? for in that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition their <hi>Summum bonum</hi> would have been the pleaſures of this life. If not <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> they either acted at their Death according to Conſcience, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Conſcience; if againſt Conſcience we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they wittingly went about to damn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without remedy, dying in Perjury known to themſelves as ſuch, to Judge this is very uncharitable,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32724:3"/>if they acted according to Conſcience, profeſſing Innocency for what they were Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndemned for, and yet were guilty; then were they the moſt groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or of the weakeſt Capacity or Judgment of any that ever were Executed, and proceeded by palpable Contradictions: they muſt have believed a God, and not believed his Eſſence, nor believed his Eſſential Verity; For he cannot believe God to be eſſential Verity, who believes that he can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe a Lye; wherefore whoſoever calls God to Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a Lye, and acts according to Conſcience, groſly and palpably contradicts himſelf, and to Judge this of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> would argue groſs folly and ignorance in any knowing Perſon, no reaſonable Creature in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe Circumſtances could have dared to appear im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before the Throne of the Eternal, Great, and All-ſeeing Judge of the Living and the Dead, as it were glorying in the moſt Uncharitable falſities that ever yet were pronounced by Men. If Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, did they not in vindicating themſelves Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and Condemn the Law and Common Juſtice of the Nation, and with Vanity, Countenance, Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Infidelities, and Treaſons againſt both King and Kingdom, the blackeſt of all Crimes? Can you believe they ſhould think God can comply with any, even the leaſt ſin in any Circumſtance? is it not moſt deteſtable to his Nature? is not ſin the greateſt ill, and even the only ill, and God the greateſt Good, and the only abſolute goodneſs? Sin a negation of all good, a <hi>non Entity,</hi> a want of all due rectitude in any action done, and <hi>malum per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe,</hi> God goodneſs it ſelf, and perfection it ſelf, the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>Exiſtence</hi> as he defined himſelf in Scripture <hi>Ego ſum qui ſum,</hi> the only abſolute being or entity, from whom it emanes or flowes to all Creatures? What then more oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32724:3"/>than God and Sin? Were it not then Sacrilegious to avouch that God cannot be diſpleaſed with a Creature when he ſins, or that he can approve a Lye? Beſides, if a Lye were in any Circumſtance to be allowed by God, it would argue deficiency in God, as that any thing ſhould be poſſible to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed out of the Sphere of Divine Activity, by aſſiſtance of the Divel the Father of Lies; Nor could his Omniſcience be leſs queſtionable, as reaſonably imputing to it an ignorance of effecting his deſigns, but by the unjuſt ways of iniquity; likewiſe would his Providential Goodneſs and Juſtice be cenſured, as allowing ſin the <hi>medium</hi> to obtain Heaven, nay himſelf who is the end of all Righteouſneſs; This is Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and to Arraign God in all his Attributes; this is ſo abſurd, that it will be folly to ſpend more time in this Argument; or to believe it poſſible, that Men whoſe Educations and Breeding have been in Schools, ſhould be either ſo ignorant as to hold ſuch ſilly Opinions, or ſo wicked Chriſtians as to ſeem to believe the higheſt Crimes damnable, and Sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lyes, Perjuries, Treaſons, and Blaſphemies, as meritorious Virtues, alleadging God as Witneſs in juſtification of ſuch infernal Acts, horrid to every Chriſtian Ear, abominable to Common ſenſe, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the very hight of nature. And that this is not only according to the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by <hi>Harcourt,</hi> that <hi>no ill is to be done, that good may come thereof;</hi> but is alſo the Doctrine of the <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> You may learn from Father <hi>Berry</hi> an eminent <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> and modern Author, in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Book called <hi>The Sollitu de of Philargie,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by Anthority, and not called in again as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana</hi>'s, and was wrote for the practice and daily Meditations of all ſorts of People, where to expreſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32724:4"/>the mallice of Sin, he ſays that <hi>it were better that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels were annihilated, and that all the World periſh, than to offend Godiby the leaſt Sin, even of an idle word;</hi> this conſidered, the inhumane expreſſions of your Paper no ways touch me, nor is my amazement, as yours, grounded on their Proclaiming themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonent (for if ſo, then to manifeſt it publickly to the whole World upon ſo ſolemn an occaſion, was but Juſtice to others, as well as to themſelves) but at your not crediting ſuch pregnant circumſtances, at your belying and ſlandering the Dead, and your guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty detractions which I believed inconſiſtent with the Principles of Chriſtians, and therefore admire it in the practice of a Chriſtian Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Scripture and all true Morality teach us, to do as we would be done unto, to Judge no otherwiſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers than we would be Judged by others; and I thought it the Principle and due practice of every Chriſtian to make the beſt expoſition of the Words and Actions of others, to make the charitableſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation words will bear, eſpecially the words of dying men, delivered with Chriſtian Courage, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, Reſolution, and Conſtancy, and not Spider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to ſuck venome from ſweeteſt Flowers. Can you believe they proceeded ſo maliciouſly at the hour of Death? I have ſo much Charity for you, as to think, that were you under the ſame Circumſtances as they were when they pronounced thoſe Speeches, immedialely expecting Death, not then to be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any Allurements of Pleaſure, Greatneſs or Fortune, not capable of Worldly Advancement, or vanity, dreading the conſequences of Eternity, you would then detract ſuch raſh Judgments, even of the worſt of Men, and conclude it a time to be ſerious, and not to uſe Quirks and Equivocations to deceive,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32724:4"/>or impiouſly to hide truth. Now as to what you alleadge to prove, they might well be guilty, for all their Proteſtations to the contrary is very frivolous. <hi>We muſt believe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that every of them recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved plenary Abſolution of all their ſins, from their Birth to this day, upon which Abſolution they may affirm themſelves as free from, and as innocent of any Crime laid to their charge, as the Child unborn, becauſe whatever the Crime is, 'tis forgiven.</hi> So not to count you very malicious, I am forced, as the leſs evil, to think you very ignorant. Where did you ever read in any <hi>Cathol.</hi> Author, that after Abſolution for any Sin, the Penitent might think himſelf as innocent of it as the Child unborn? How then can he ſwear it? who knows not that when by the Prophet 'twas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to <hi>David</hi> that his Sin was forgiven him, yet he was not ſo innocent, but that God puniſhed him afterwards temporally for it, as in Scripture is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared? and who knows with ſuch certainty as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for an Oath, whether he had a due Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neceſſary to Abſolution? <hi>No Man knows whether he be worthy of Love or Hatred from God,</hi> is the ſenſe of the Scripture, and Doctrine of the Catholick Church, and that we muſt work our Salvation with fear and trembling, with Chriſtian humility, and not preſumptive confidence. Moreover ſhould it be granted, that Abſolution before hand might juſtifie that expreſſion of being as innocent as the Child un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, yet could it not juſtifie Mr. <hi>Whitebread,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>to pray to God to bleſs his Majesty, is all the harm that he ever intended or imagined againſt him; and that he never did learn, teach, or believe, that it is Lawful upon any occaſion or practice whatſoever to deſign or contrive the death of his Majeſty, or any hurt to his perſon;</hi> Mr. Harcourt ſaying, <hi>We hold it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32724:5"/>in all Caſes unlawful to Kill or Murther any perſon whatſoever, much more our lawful King.</hi> Mr. Gavan, <hi>I do atteſt that I never in my life did machine or contrive either the depoſition or death of the King.</hi> Mr. Turner, <hi>I never accus'd my ſelf in confeſſion of any thing that I am charged with.</hi> Mr. Fenwick, <hi>I know nothing of it,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Of plotting the Kings death) <hi>but what I have learned from Mr.</hi> Oates <hi>and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and what comes originally from them.</hi> Mr. Langhorn, <hi>I neither am, nor ever was at any time, or times guilty, ſo much as in my moſt ſecret thoughts of any Treaſon, or miſpriſion of Treaſon whatſoever.</hi> Theſe ſayings, even ſuppoſing a Revelation, that Abſolution has taken away all guilt, ſo as to render them as innocent as the Child unborn cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed without having been ever innocent of the fact charged againſt them; for even the abſolute power of God cannot effect that not to have been which was, nor could their Abſolution take away their memory, or allow them to declare they knew not that which was in their memory. But ſay you, <hi>If they ſinned in that their declaration of Innocency, yet they might ſafely do it, having a power to abſolve each other juſt as they were going out of the World, as I believe they did when they laid their heads together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Give me leave to teach you again what is the <hi>Catholick Doctrine,</hi> for I find you have very groſs miſtakes therein. Obſerve then Sir, That there is not one <hi>Catholick</hi> nor Chriſtian Author I believe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the World that holds it ſufficient to have the words of Abſolution pronounced over him, but that then is requiſite in the Penitent <hi>a real averſion, deteſtation, or turning away in his heart from ſin,</hi> and <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to God,</hi> to render him a fit or diſpoſed ſubject to receive the effect of Abſolution; Is it then likely
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32724:5"/>that any Chriſtia ſhould be ſo preſumptive at the hour of his death, as wilfully to ſin upon confidence of ſuch diſpoſition immediately after, knowing that his ſorrow muſt be from a ſupernatural motive, and not in his power, but by the grace of God whom he then offends? this is certainly the higheſt preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imaginable, and not to be paralled. What Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner knowing he had but three Moments to live, would make uſe of two to offend God upon confidence of the laſt? Who can think ſo meanly of God, as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine him ſo ſubſervient to Man, as that he as it were may lure down from Heaven ſupernatural grace at his will and pleaſure? who has that faculty to love and hate the ſame thing ſo immediately, as if the one were a diſpoſition to the other its contrary, and not Sin the puniſhment of preceding Sins, but grace as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reward? How ſtands this with that place of Scripture, <hi>Neque volentis neque currentis ſed miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentis eſt dei?</hi> What more abſurd and wicked than ſuch proceeding, or more nonſenſical and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuppoſe it, not only in any learned Chriſtian, but even in any illiterate <hi>Mahometan?</hi> this is to bid farewell to all Charity, Religion, Reaſon, Prudence and Common ſenſe. But ſay you, <hi>If to Rob, Spoil, kill Proteſtants, burn their Cities, and depoſe Kings, be no ſin, but good and lawful, then they might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves innocent, though never ſo guilty, for</hi> Romaniſts <hi>tell us 'tis no ſin to take from thoſe they count Haereticks all they have.</hi> For this you cite the <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> Councel, <hi>ſub Innoc.</hi> 2. and <hi>Syloc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter N.</hi> 23. <hi>Q.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. Firſt in Anſwer to it, we muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Articles of Faith declared in Councels, and the Conſtitutions of Government or Laws; The firſt are <hi>unalterable, infallible,</hi> and <hi>irreſiſtable,</hi> the other <hi>fallible, alterable,</hi> and <hi>reſiſtable,</hi> and may be ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32724:6"/>and abrogated, and are ſo upon ſundry occaſions. For example, the Counſel of the Apoſtles Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned that Doctrine, holding Circumciſion neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, this Article of Faith can never be oppoſed, but the Decree they made againſt <hi>eating of ſtrangled meats and blood,</hi> became quickly of no force, and is now wholly abrogated.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Canon Laws ſo farr forth as they relate to temporals oblige; or are in force only there, where they are received, or approved by the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Authority of the Kingdom, Principality or State (and where do you find the Three States of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the antient and preſent Government of this Kingdom, conſenting to depoſe Kings for Haereſie, or to diſpoſe of their Lands, &amp;c.) and ſuch Canons muſt be formally promulged there by the Governing Authority in due method, otherwiſe they are of no validity; this is ſeen by the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> which though it be received throughout the Catholick World as to its Decrees concerning Belief, or Articles of Faith, yet as to, in other Canons, or Conſtitutions of Government, is in ſome places wholly rejected, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places in part received, in others wholly. And this Kingdom when Catholick in part, rejected the Canons of the Third Councel of <hi>Lateran</hi> for making <hi>Children legitimate after Marriage, born before,</hi> ſaying <hi>Nolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s leges Anglia mutari.</hi> So that upon the whole matter it implies no more, then to ſay that any King, Prince, or State may make or agree to ſuch penal Laws againſt Diſſenters in Religion, as they in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhall think fit, and ſo may either take, or reject the advice of Pope or Councel.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That Canon of the <hi>Lateran Counſel</hi> was made againſt the Subordinate, and Fuditary Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> as the Prince of <hi>Berne,</hi> Earl
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32724:6"/>
               <hi>Cominge,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Foix,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Tholous,</hi> who then countenanced and abetted the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> the Emperors of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> and moſt Kings thereto conſenting by their Ambaſſadors, and their Authority uſed to ſuppreſs thoſe <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> and to prevent diſſention and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the Empire of <hi>France,</hi> and other Kingdoms; this was the motive of that Canon which begins, <hi>Si Dominus terrae,</hi> &amp;c. not naming <hi>Kings, Emperors,</hi> or <hi>abſolute Princes,</hi> but <hi>inferior Lords,</hi> nor <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> but <hi>Lands Terras,</hi> and not <hi>Regna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Were ſuch a Canon in force in <hi>England,</hi> yet could not ſuch a Law be executed againſt the King, who was never denounced Haeretick, nor any perſonal Excommunication pronounced againſt him, or was ever heard, or admoniſhed by Pope or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel (the fame may be ſaid of all the Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi>) ſo that I ſay, were any ſuch Canon admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, even by Act of Parliament, or Conſtitutions of this Kingdom, it would not reach his Majeſty nor <hi>England</hi> as guilty.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Though I ſhould ſuppoſe contrary to truth, that ſuch a Canon did reach the King and this Kingdom, yet could it not be executed by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons, no more than a Jeſuite or Prieſt can by a private Perſon or Authority be hang'd, drawn; and quarter'd: He or they muſt be firſt publickly Tryed, and legally Condemned and then Executed only by the appointed Executioner; that Canon then doth no ways Impower or Authorize in the leaſt any perſon living, Jeſuite or other, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate thoſe Crimes you mention, wherefore upon many demonſtrative Reaſons, thoſe aforementioned Crimes muſt by all be accounted or denied horrid, and unchriſtian, and no one can juſtly declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32724:7"/>innocent who hath committed them. Next as to your proving it law ful by Dr. <hi>John Dun-Scotus, &amp;c.</hi> To Swear with Equivocations upon juſt Cauſe, makes not at all to your purpoſe nor what you alleadge of <hi>Bonnacina;</hi> For the Jeſuites in their laſt Speeches tell you with great Aſſeverations that they make uſe of no Equivocation, mental Reſervation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor from thoſe Authors can it be proved, that any one may Swear contrary to the ſenſe the words properly bear, but all you can deduce is, that is words Amphilogious, doubtful, or of two ſenſes, I may ſwear to that ſenſe I think the truth, though it perhaps be underſtood in another ſenſe by him that hears me; and this only upon a juſt cauſe (as <hi>Abraham</hi> did about <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife, calling her his Siſter) which he there explains.</p>
            <p>The Jeſuites proteſted they ſpoke in the plain ſenſe the words bear, and averred it with great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations, and I believe you, nor any body living, can find any proper, or other ſenſe to their words, but that of Innocency: and I did hope with <hi>Fenwick, That Chriſtian Charity would not have let you thought, that by the</hi> laſt Act <hi>of his life he would caſt away his Soul, by ſealing up his laſt breath with a damnable lye;</hi> Were not this greater want of Charity, than to ſay, He that dies an obſtinate Haeretick cannot be ſaved. The uſual Objection againſt <hi>Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place you cite <hi>Soto,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Mendacium ſi non habet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>A Lye, if it have no other malice than that of falſehood, it is no mortal ſin?</hi> What is this more than to ſay, every Lye is not a mortal Sin; for every Lye has the malice of falſhood; and doth this argue, or can any one deduce from hence, that no Lye is a mortal Sin; that a Lye that has beſides the malice of falſhood, the malice of prejudice or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32724:7"/>wrong to my Neighbour, a falſe accuſation of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by proteſting my own Innocency with a Lye, or to lye with perjury and imprecations upon falſhood, can any inferr from thence, theſe not to be mortal? and ſuch had been the Lyes of the Jeſuites, were they guilty of what they were accuſed. Laſtly, You ground your calumny upon theſe words, <hi>Certum eſt obligationem hujas praecepti,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It is certain that the Obligation of this precept</hi> (to conceal what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd in Confeſſion) <hi>in no Caſe, and for no end, even the defence of the Commonwealth from very great ill, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spiritual or Temporal; can be violated or broken,</hi> to this you alleadge <hi>Durand, Scotus,</hi> and many more. What of all this? did the Jeſuites, if guilty, know of the Plot only by hearing the Confeſſions of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? If ſo, they could not be Actors in it, as they were accuſed to be, and Condemned for; where do you find a Precept of not revealing or owning my own Actions, although I had confeſſed them before? Now give me leave here (mention being made of this Precept) to ſhew you that this Precept is ſo far from being of any ill conſequence to any Kingdom, as that on the contrary, 'tis very advantagious, a great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance, and no incouragement to Treaſon. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Sacramentally confeſſeth Treaſon owns it a Crime; the Prieſt that has a precept of concealing it, has alſo a precept not to abſolve him unleſs he hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily repent, and if the Treaſon be only intended, he muſt indiſpenſably require him to deſiſt from ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, he muſt with all poſſible diligence exhort him to deteſt ſuch Intention or Treaſon in his heart, and to diſcover his Complices, if he have any, as in Conſcience he is abſolutely bound to do, here is Confeſſion by the admonition and direction of the Paſtor and Spiritual Phyſitian of his Soul (who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32724:8"/>hereby knows the Diſeaſe and State of his Soul) a great means to his Spiritual Cure, to caſt out of his Heart all Treaſonable thoughts, and to prevent the Actions, but if there were not that precept of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſie, who would confeſs to be Accuſed and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached? 'Tis Confeſſion that is the great ſecurity of all Catholick Kingdoms from Treaſon; for when any guilty in fact or intention come to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. they are preſſed to declare their Complices, and obliged to retract and hinder what is not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected therein, knowing they cannot be Abſolved without it, whereby moſt Treaſons are timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented. For this Reaſon we find that ſucceſs in Rebellion againſt Government, has commonly been joyned with Rebellion in Religion, as pretended Reformation in Religion and Rebellion againſt their Sovereign, ſet up together in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Principalities of the Empire; whereas Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, remaining ſuch, contradict by Treaſon their own Principles, and muſt acknowledge ſuch practice damnable; wherefore had the Jeſuites been guilty, you would have had from them an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Crime, as done or acted contrary to their Conſcience and Principles of their Religion; but 'tis no Principle of any Religion to accuſe ones ſelf falſly. Wherefore wonder not that they ſhould rather dye profeſſing Innocency to the Crimes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt them, with hope of Salvation and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of God for all their real Offences, than to live by his Majeſties Pardon with falſe accuſation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others, and diſpleaſure or anger of God. And I muſt not wonder to find their Words and Speeches ſo miſrepreſented, whereas even the Word of God is dayly traduced by falſe Gloſſes, to the ruine of many. And what wonder that thoſe Five
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32724:8"/>Jeſuites, and many more, though never <hi>ſo Loyal</hi> have been thus Condemned, and Executed as Traitors to his Majeſty. Where by pretended Juſtice and courſe of Law, one of the beſt of Kings has been Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Executed as a Traitor to his Country. By thus ſuffering they have as Chriſtians imitated Chriſt, and as loyal Subjects imitated their King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, God bleſs King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
